Uh, FEC, and we look forward to your submission.
We've got you for five minutes, but please leave some time for questions.
Will do.
So, the Fair Trading Amendment Bill has, in my view,
very admirable objectives. Two key objectives as
I read the explanatory note are ensuring
that the Fair Trading Act is fit for purpose
as digital markets evolve,
and secondly, enabling efficient and effective
enforcement.
And by efficient, I take that to mean
cost effective.
Effective really means timely.
In my view, unfortunately, the Fair Trading Act has become
ineffective in relation to digital markets, particularly in the
case of overseas online trades,
and hugely costly to try and enforce against overseas online traders.
In my written submission, I give the example of
Viagogo, the online ticket reseller.
And just to give a just very brief overview, Commission wanted to
stop
some conduct by Viagogo in terms of the
way that they were offering tickets for resale.
Brought a case in 2018, wanted an injunction.
Viagogo avoided service, said, "You've got to service in Switzerland,
go through The Hague convention, do it through diplomatic channels."
Argued in the meantime that the High Court didn't have jurisdiction to grant an
injunction, actually won that in the High Court.
Court of Appeal had to take that on appeal to the Court of Appeal.
Viagogo took all steps to try and resist the
proceedings, resisted discovery, sought to delay the
proceedings. The Commission said that they took an obstructive attitude.
I
don't know the rights and wrongs of that, but certainly the High Court made some
critical comments.
Continued their defense,
despite being penalized for essentially the same conduct in Australia in
2020. So the case took six years, from
2018 to 2024, and then
since then it's gone further on appeal.
And cases like that are hugely expensive and time-consuming,
very hard for the Commerce Commission to run more than one or two cases like
that at the same time if they
involve that much expense. And in the meantime, you've got ongoing harm to
consumers over many years
if online traders can't be quickly prevented
from engaging in misleading conduct.
Now fortunately,
we've got a good model in other legislation for how to deal with this.
So the Financial Markets Conduct Act provides a
model in relation to how to deal with misleading conduct in financial markets.
So the FMA is the regulator for misleading conduct in financial markets,
Commerce Commission for everything else, misleading conduct in other markets.
And what you can do under the Financial Markets Conduct Act
is the regulator can give notice of a stop order,
so the trader has to stop the misleading conduct immediately.
They can challenge
that order in the courts, but at least the consumer harm is prevented in the
meantime. And if the trader doesn't stop the conduct, then the
regulator can, as part of the stop order notice,
stop the trader from providing services in New Zealand
to New Zealand consumers at all. The Financial
Markets Authority has exercised its stop order power
to prevent a Dubai corporation from offering securities when the
public was misled. I refer to that case, that example, in
my written submission.
And so that enabled the FMA, in that case, within two months
of finding out about the misleading conduct, to stop securities
being offered.
So
my essential argument is that the Commerce Commission should have the same
power to
give stop notices as
the FMA has.
Same sort of situation to stop misleading conduct.
And in my view, that's a far more important reform than just
increasing the penalties under the act.
Now, I don't have a problem with what's currently proposed in
the Amendment Bill. I'm just saying that if you really want to achieve the
objectives of the
Bill, of ensuring effective and efficient
enforcement of the act, and if you really want to achieve the
objective in the Bill of ensuring that
the Fair Trading Act is fit for purpose as digital markets
evolve, then you need these stop order powers more than you need the
increased penalties, though I don't mind the increased penalties.
Thanks, John. Thanks. Quick question from me.
The stop order power,
you're saying FMA already has it.
Yeah.
If the Commerce Commission have it, are you saying it would...
I'm just making sure we're not duplicating powers.
Would it be a separate type for different entities?
Yeah. So both the Commerce Commission would have as well as the FMA.
The FMA, of course, only regulate misleading conduct in
relation to financial markets,
whereas the Commerce Commission regulates misleading conduct everywhere else.
Okay.
So it's to try and have consistency and ensure that the
Commission has the same toolbox.
Yeah. Thank you. Your submission's very clear and very comprehensive-
Mm
... for a person's submission, so I just want to thank you for that, and that'll be
duly noted.
Very good. Any other questions from the committee?
Unfortunately, we have met time, but-
Okay
... yeah.
No worries.
Yeah, that's time. Thanks for coming in.
Thank you.
Okay.
Jayden, are we, or Taryn, are we back to Max, or are we- Uh,
we- Is Max here or not? Yeah, we can see him come in. Okay.
And then we have Internet New Zealand. Fantastic.
Internet New Zealand, are they in the room?
Are they joining via internet?
Line is very good.
Good morning, Vivian.
Sorry, Isabel.
Yes. Vivian's here. Good morning. And Isabel.
Good morning. We've got you for 10 minutes. We're in your hands.
Yeah. Great.
But it goes quick, so please leave time for questions.
Thank you. Okay. Well, thank you for hearing our submission.
As you probably know, Internet New Zealand is an independent
purpose-driven organization in the community sector, but
we're responsible for administering and maintaining the .nz
domain name system, the DNS-
Mm
... on behalf of all New Zealanders.
And
a critical part to that is maintaining the .nz
registry and the infrastructure that enables .nz
websites and email addresses to connect
globally.
That's sort of a deeply technical process.
But we maintain a database of domain name registration
data, providing name service to publish the zone file
throughout the internet.
We have a subsidiary called the Domain Name Commission.
It's an independent subsidiary. They're kind of our regulatory body.
And they oversee the .nz domain name market, enforcing
the .nz rules, authorize and deauthorize registrars
who retail domain names, and investigate
complaints, and they operate a dispute resolution service.
So,
we are actively involved with our international peers on best
practice and response to scams. You can imagine that's a very big
issue globally right now, and how best
to respond to abusers of the domain name
system,
usually called DNS abuse.
So, we're a technical expert who provide
advice on public policy topics related to the internet and the digital
environment. I wanted to just
make that introduction because our interest is deep,
but relatively small in the context of this
whole
sub- the whole area that you're considering.
And I wanted to hand over to Isabel, who'll talk through the
specific feedback in relationship to this bill.
Thanks, Isabel.
Thank you. I'm going to introduce
the two organizations, InternetNZ, the
registry, and the Domain Name Commission, so people can
understand the nature of the tools that we have
because we have got a request for a-
Great
... clarification of the definition.
So that's why I'm
just explaining a bit more about the powers.
InternetNZ, through the operation of the
.nz registry, actually has the
technical ability to disrupt
scams at the domain name system level,
and that is through disabling a domain name
by putting it on a hold or suspending it.
When that happens, the entire domain name is
taken down. We can't carve out specific
offending content or take
down...
We can only take down the whole service that's enabled by that
domain name.
So that's the work technically that InternetNZ
can do at the .nz registry level.
How it's actually enabled is that the Domain Name Commission
plays that oversight role, and they are
the entity that can take the decision to suspend or cancel a
domain name.
I'm going to move into the clarification
that we're seeking. But I just want to reconfirm that
due to the shifts in the industry,
the domain name system
internationally is looking at disrupting, particularly phishing and
malware, and the Domain Name Commission is looking into
its role, how it can better respond to technical abuse.
So, the clarification that we're seeking is that we
propose a new definition that better
describes the type of services included in the current
wording, which is internet domain name
registration service.
Those words, "internet domain name registration service," would
normally mean the registrar that retails to the
public, when in fact it's actually central
top-level domain name sys- um, operators, like
InternetNZ, who runs the top
of .nz. So they have the full
oversight across the whole space.
We're saying that it's much more effective if a registry
is also
able to have the benefits of the safe harbor, and at the
moment,
it's not clear that we're included.
So I'm not going to read out the whole basis
of our written submission, but we have proposed wording
there. We say that the policy intent is better
achieved if it's clarified that both
the wholesalers and retailers of
domain names are covered by the safe harbor.
And we are in an environment where
organizations like the Domain Name Commission and other threat
providers are also doing
scam prevention. So we want to extend- The definition
of registration services to those providing
oversight and compliance services.
So I hope
that nuance can be adapted and that will
better provide for the intent of the legislation, the
policy intent, so that all of the key parties can
actually obtain that safe harbor. Thank you.
Thank you. We've got a question from Todd Stevens.
Oh, no, mine was just a comment to say thanks for your submission.
Yeah, we'll definitely take that on board.
And you've outlined your case pretty clearly, so thank
you.
So just the other key point we wanted to make
relates to the trusted flagger network set out the accompanying
regulatory impact statement as a non-legislative
option that's currently being scoped.
We recommend the trusted flagger network could be given greater
status and legislated.
Giving the trusted flagger network a statutory mandate would provide
entities acting in scam disruption, including the Domain Name
Commission, the assurance that the actions are proportionate and
meet the legal threshold for safe harbor.
So I think that was the second key point we wanted to bring to your attention.
Very good. Okay. Thank you very much for your presentation, Vivian and Isabel.
We have met time, but, appreciate that.
We'll feed into our select committee process.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
Have we got Kari Quince?
Just joining.
Kia ora, Kari. Are you there?
Kia ora. Can you hear me?
Yes, we can. We've only got you for five minutes.
You've got a pretty comprehensive three pages.
Can I just encourage you to just focus on your top two or three points?
Because time will go very fast.
That's okay. Yeah.
Can you still hear me?
Yes.
Okay, sweet. Okay.
I'm not fully against this bill or
anything.
I agree with stopping big multinationals from
treating fines as a cost of doing business,
giving the Commerce Commission a faster enforcement tool,
fighting online scams and updating product
safety standards faster.
But I have a few worries.
I'm worried about the overwhelming volume of legislation
being rushed through Parliament.
When laws move at this pace, frequently
strip back treaty protections, it creates
deep anxiety across our community.
Compared to major constitutional changes, a consumer
bill might not look like the primary concern, but when
Parliament moves in haste, officials neglect
critical mechanisms buried in the fine print.
So why would citizens not scrutinize
every detail?
Under the banner of consumer protection, this bill shifts
enforcement
from a criminal regime requiring proof beyond
reasonable doubt with $600,000
fine caps to a civil regime with a lower
balance of probabilities standard
and penalties up to $5 million. This
expansion comes right off the back of
a recent public sector budget cut to the Commerce
Commission. Will
the Commission actually have the resources needed to manage this massive
increase in litigation capacity, or
will enforcement simply fail to
private
competitors filing costly civil lawsuits?
In primary industries like farming and fishing, minor
operational slips like an uncalibrated
scale on a boat or a packing typo on
produce become easy targets. As the Insurance
Council of New Zealand highlighted, standard
statutory liability insurance does not cover
civil pecuniary penalties. While
multinationals absorb civil
litigation out of global reserves,
local Kiwi operators and Māori enterprises face an
uninsurable liability gap. How can we
justify exposing local operators to sudden
liquidation over an honest operational mistake?
The most severe oversight, however, is how the regime
interacts with Whenua Māori. While Section
342 of Te Tiriti Whenua Māori
Act protects land titles from direct
execution, this bill creates an
indirect economic
backdoor.
A multimillion-dollar penalty forced onto a trading arm
triggers corporate insolvency. The High Court
liquidator can seize fishing quota, livestock, and
machinery, or lease out the Whenua to third
parties to pay court debts. What is the value of
protecting land titles on paper if the commercial
engine funding Whenua housing, environmental
care, and local jobs is wiped out underneath it?
I urge the committee to- Direct officials to engage
directly with Te Puni Kōkiri to
assess these indirect commercial impacts to
include and express
savings
or
safe harbor provision protecting existing rights under Te
Ture Whenua Māori Act and Te Tiriti o Waitangi.
Tena koutou.
Thank you, Kari, for your submission.
Are there any questions from members?
No.
No. Thank you. I think your points were pretty clear, and you certainly put a lot
of information in your submission, so thank you for engaging in the process.
Thank you.
We've got FINCAP
in the room. Welcome.
You must be Jake.
Yeah. Apologies from Fleur,
was on leave when we got the call for this, so-
No problem. We've got you for 10 minutes, but yeah, obviously if you have a bit of
time for questions, it can be quite helpful.
Awesome. Thank you.
So if you're unfamiliar, I know many here have worked with financial mentors and us
before. Thank you for your time working with us.
But FINCAP, we are out there as an umbrella organization across
currently around 183 services who support financial mentors
in their communities around the country.
There's over 700 financial mentors out there.
I'm here with you today because I often get calls from financial mentors or emails
from financial mentors saying, "I just can't believe this unacceptable thing from a
debt collector continues to happen, and I can't really find a way through it."
And it really aligns with the objectives of this bill, focusing on it in
the written submission.
Also highlight we've got our Voices report out tomorrow.
In that, we've seen 121% increase in debt in our
system over the last five years. We're almost at a billion dollars of debt
in all sorts of different forms, and some of those, although quite small, can cause
a lot of problems in people's lives
as debt collectors pursue them.
60% of mentors encounter clients experiencing issues with debt collectors
often or very often,
34% sometimes. So it's pretty universal out there for the financial mentors.
86% had seen debt collectors make demands for repayment that prevented clients from
affording food
or other essentials, and two-thirds had seen excessively frequent
contact from debt collectors, which is unconstructive really
when you look at someone being unable to pay.
So we do think that debt collection is a legitimate part of our economy, but the
rules around it need tidying up to stop needlessly harmful
contact that doesn't benefit anyone.
I've been working on this for coming up six years.
I know there was a good look at this as well in the review that led to the
introduction to high-cost lending protections,
but we constantly get these reasons why work stalls in this space,
and I'm really asking you to seize the moment and the objectives of this bill to do
something in this space.
The cost of living keeps biting people, and we need better law
to prevent harassment and coercion in years to come from debt collectors
where people have gotten into debt that they can't handle and didn't anticipate
they weren't going to be able to handle.
FINCAP and financial mentors were glad to work with Minister Bailey through the
Consumer Protection Partnership Forum, setting up a group with officials and
getting into this a bit. That led to some good work and some good
discussion. In the targeted consultation for this, there was a good look at
harassment and coercion, but the timelines for this piece of work that
led to this bill
meant it ended up being much narrower than the few things that were put in front of
people.
Again, we're stalled. It leaves households constantly exposed, and
really that exposure in terms of harassment and coercion, which I'm focusing on, is
that
we don't see a good case to take complaints to the Commerce Commission
about these problems because the Commerce Commission is left without a penalty for
these two things.
So it's not economic for them
to go to the court and get an order in one instance saying, "Hey, you
shouldn't do that."
The debt collector then says, "Or else what?" There might be something, although
it's a high bar, around getting some money back to a person where it's been taken
in circumstances where it shouldn't.
But again, is it really a good deterrent?
It doesn't make sense for the Commerce Commission to put resources into it unless
they're backed with a penalty
in those circumstances.
And yeah, as I said, financial mentors aren't taking those cases as often as they
would because they know there's a bit of a dead end there.
When I talk about coercion, I'm talking about debt collectors saying they won't
leave your house until you agree to their demand or the minimum
demand.
Debt collectors yelling abuse down the phone at a financial mentor who's just
asking for proof of a debt that they claim someone owes.
And we get a taste of financial mentor, financial mentors see a bit of the
harassment too. Not all of it. You sort of get different reactions once a
financial mentor gets involved, but occasionally some of those systems are so
sloppy at debt collectors that we see financial mentors' numbers associated with a
file, and that gets put onto the computer.
They get automatically dialed, automatic messages, texts, emails,
and then sometimes you try and call back and ask, "Hey,
I've had this contact," and the contact center you go back to is so hard to
navigate. You can't actually respond to the request for contact,
which is a bit ridiculous.
We also get situations where an agreement is made after contact is made, but then
the automatic calls, automatic dialing doesn't stop because someone doesn't know
how to stop it in the system at the debt collector.
It has real consequences. People just stop answering contact in
general. It means we see drop-off from financial mentors trying
to support someone, because if someone doesn't recognize the number, they don't
pick up their phone. They're changing email addresses and phone numbers because
it's just so impractical to live when they're getting constant demands to pay
something that they've clearly stated or given evidence that they can't
pay.
Sometimes as well, the harassment will wear people down and they'll give away their
rent money, their food money, power money.
The consequences of that hardship will intensify and they're just back in the
cycle. It leads to more hospitalizations,
strain in relationships with those partners, family, and friends that they lean on
at times as they try and get this problem sorted.
And also that sobering research we've put in a written submission around
suicidal ideation.
Again, that's in the written submission.
Also put forward in our submission that there needs to be a lot more
guidance in the space and perhaps across a range of regulators.
It was mentioned before of sort of the crossover that happens in terms of what the
law says with the financial markets and also the broader markets.
ACCC guidelines in Australia are pretty good.
They're much clearer about where the line is.
It would help us when we're negotiating with debt collectors.
It would help them too in terms of what's expected, and it would mean less
having to go to the Commerce Commission and go through all the processes there that
are very costly and timely,
time-consuming.
And also stressing we really support the penalties going up, although we
make the point in our submission that you should look at the Australian penalties
too. We do speak with some complaints, people at Australian
businesses at times, and they sort of comment that, "Hey, we see less
complaints from New Zealand and a bit different regulator there too," so don't want
to be a soft target or maybe not having as much attention on compliance
here as there is in Australia.
Lastly, I just wanted to touch on, there's been reasons put down for delaying this
work on applying penalties to coercion and harassment in briefings from
officials that have been released.
There is some
piece of work that needs to be done around the definition of harassment, it seems.
That's all good, but it's nothing that can't be worked through if it's prioritized.
And to my understanding, a good piece of work or review of the Fair Trading Act as
a whole is long overdue.
Mm-hmm.
These things do need to be prioritized.
So many households are struggling with cost of living pressures right now that will
have a long tail.
And it should also be noted from reading that advice, I didn't spot anything in
there that really justified not getting on with penalties for coercion.
There was talk about harassment, but there's no reason you can't go for coercion
now. So, putting it there as something the committee might be able to
recommend. Thank you for your time.
Thanks, Jake. Elena.
We're
... I'm hoping to get y- this will be your only submission,
so we will receive advice back on this about what the gap in the law
is. There's unconscionable conduct at one end, there's
unfair terms, but you're talking about conduct
outside of a transaction, but over the course
of the price that a transaction would cost a consumer.
So are you looking for regulation around,
like is it a regulatory making power that sets out kind of what
coercion would be acceptable? What sort of
manipulation is just normal commercial practice, or are you looking for
a blanket ban and then enforcement at the
concom level?
Yeah, I guess a blanket ban technically exists right now-
Yeah
... in that as it's written, it's a penalty for that which then gives the regulator
a bit more space for guidance to say-
Yeah
... this is what's expected and then can adapt that as inevitably markets will
change.
Do you think ACCC style fines
for conduct that can be levied at the regulator level or do you think it's
court process fines?
Looking at Australia, it seems like they've got the whole menu and they adapt
to the circumstances. I know this was largely talked around supermarkets and those
two geographies have very different structures, so it might be
different depending on who's done what.
So the more the better is probably our position there in terms of
infringements if those are going to be most useful to deter
through to criminal.
We'll seek advice on this, and I anticipate that we will be told that the
formulation of the law as it is now will
dampen this kind of conduct in the market.
Do you think the law as it's formulated now will do enough?
Not really, no. No. I think just when a debt collector is
at someone's house or they're getting trained, it's not getting through to that
point and I don't think a change in penalty's going to change that at the moment.
Yeah.
Thank you. Just a supplementary on the back of that.
Do you think there's a bit of space for, you used the word harmonization in your
submission between Australia's processes and ours?
Yeah. There is a study that was done sort of
working with us, and it looked at the definition adopting undue,
which brings over a bit of case law from Australia, and that has some good
definition.
Harassment is an interesting concept here.
It is legitimate to follow up with someone and say, "We assert you owe
this. You need to get back to us. Here's how to get back to us."
Undue goes to another level where you're well aware of the
circumstances.
Yeah.
And you can constantly keep going.
Hey, thanks so much for your submission and the work you and your team do.
It's fantastic.
Thank you. Thanks all.
We now have the Community Law Centres Aotearoa.
Karen.
Mm.
Welcome.
Tena koutou, Mr. Chair and members of the committee.
I almost want to say, yeah, what he said in some ways.
Ko Karen Hodgson tēnei. I'm pleased to be here for Community Law Centres Aotearoa.
Some of you we've worked with,
and I've been in hui with, but if you don't know, we are the national body for
the 24 Community Law Centres across the country.
We provide free legal advice across an incredibly broad range of legal issues,
and
free legal advice across a broad range of issues for people who can't afford a
lawyer. So, we provide consumer advice across the
board, including on the Fair Trading Act-
And making Commerce Commission complaints.
Just some of the examples of things we work on, we get complaints about online
sales and drip pricing, so people coming in with the full price not really
disclosed to them when they're buying online.
Parking fines, and parking companies
effectively stonewalling people when they are trying to
appeal, no evidence being provided,
and potentially misleading or coercive debt collection
practices asserting money's owed when maybe it's a money claim
in and of itself and there's no evidence, and
overstated debt collection fees, for example, like a percentage, a blanket
percentage on top of a debt. You've heard from FINCAP just
now on some of these issues, and I agree
wholeheartedly, and we see very similar issues across community
law centers.
We generally support this bill and the changes in it.
Our written submissions, as you know, focused on the change to the act to
make it a predominantly civil regime, with higher penalties, rather than
a criminal regime. The regulatory impact statement sets out really well
stakeholder views. I think we're in there, and the Commerce Commission concerns
about the effectiveness of the current regime and that it would be an
easier
road to enforce under a civil liability
regime.
I just want to also take the opportunity to raise that we, along with FINCAP
and others, are advocating for the establishment of a
financial rights legal service. We're seeing so many
really tricky and unregulated debt collection practices, but
also other kinds of financial rights issues that need
specialized financial advice, which
currently financial mentors have some access to community law centers, but
community law centers also need this specialized advice as
well.
So I'm just putting that out there if anybody's interested in knowing more.
We did raise this in relation to the financial services reform bills as
well.
And we invite members to work with us on that.
So just in connection with this, and going back to debt collection, as you know,
Section 23 doesn't have any
penalties associated with it.
It's not within the bill at the moment, but it's squarely within the objectives of
the bill,
to strengthen deterrence and compliance and greater enforcement and
greater effective and efficient enforcement.
We frequently see debt collection agencies ignoring people when they
dispute a debt, not providing evidence behind a debt,
people feeling coerced into paying, basically worn down because it's too hard to
complain or too hard to resolve the issue.
And sometimes these can have really
quite significant impacts. Jake's talked about
people going without food or what they need to do, essentials, in
order to make these payments. But also it can end up on a credit report.
We're seeing people who are ending up in civil
proceedings,
and attachment orders for debt that they barely even knew about or
haven't really had a chance to argue about.
So we've agreed with MBIE and its
consultation paper that Tier 1 penalties should apply.
We do think there should be a criminal response available because of the nature of
some of this behavior can be at that end,
and given that it includes physical force and that interpersonal nature of
the behavior when it relates to door knocking, approaches in person, that sort of
thing. We think that work should be progressed on this front,
and that this is an opportunity to really respond to this harm that's occurring in
our communities to some of the most vulnerable people.
And
we understand that time was an issue, and we really want to push back on that and
say this is incredibly important work, and we'd really like to see it
progressed. Those are really all my remarks, and I'm just open for any
questions.
Thank you. We've got first questions from Arinna Williams.
Thank you. Really appreciate your
submission. And I
am interested in other parts of it, but I just want to clarify, do you
support FINCAP's submission, particularly on
coercion in a provision to prevent as a
blanket ban and then with associated fines?
Coercion on its own?
Yeah.
I think we
haven't gone down too much thinking on that one.
I think there's a way of working it out so that you can have
harassment and coercion.
Okay.
Not opposed to it. But I'd like to see the work done on maybe working it
out so that it is harassment and coercion, but I definitely see merit in
that. We just haven't gone-
And as well for harassment, you think if they were together that would be the
appropriate way to make that-
I think if you can-- There is
a civil and
criminal regime in
the Harassment Act, or there was. And we could sort of see something
similar along those lines although, yeah, that would need some working through.
But not against that at all.
Just wonder if there's a way, whether
there's
some useful Australian case law on harassment and coercion that could be brought
over as well.
Yeah, probably just need some, that we'd need to think a bit more about that.
Can you come back to me on a different query?
Yeah. Dr. David Wilson.
I see one of your recommendations is the licensing of debt
collection agencies-
Mm
... and that that should be run by the FMA.
Mm-hmm.
How hard? And I have a supplementary question.
How hard would that be?
How hard would it be? They're already licensing a bunch of other
entities and agencies, so it would be part of that process, I imagine.
I think the things that we're recommending there are part of a
package, and I think you'd need some additional guidance
for debt collection agencies and
along the lines of the Australian guidance, to really make that work
And related to that, you were recommending some kind of organization
around financial rights and-
Mm-hmm
... and then, if you like,
how that's resolved, the resolution of that. Where would that sit?
Our previous proposal has been for that to sit in as a
unit of community law centers. We currently have other specialized centers.
Yeah.
And it could be a specialized community law center, much like in Melbourne or other
parts of Australia. And we really see that penalties
undertakings are a really great and appropriate
way to fund that service.
Thank you.
We're working at a policy level on that.
Just-
Mm-hmm
... wanted to ask you about the way, like enforcement in your
observations, having acted for clients on either
the resources that are available to ComCom to take on some of the bigger issues or
are we designing a system which isn't addressing the right end of the
market? Would be my first question.
And then interested in, you brought up sort of hidden fees, drip pricing.
Do you think as well that we've designed a system which is meant to hit the top end
of town
with bigger penalties, but what you're describing will
always by nature be one consumer who's paid $30 when
they intended to pay 10?
Mm-hmm.
Um.
Just on your first question, yeah, we do find,
the Commerce Commission has limited resources, and
the Commerce Commission has said this would make it easier.
But yeah, the question remains, I mean, I'm not really, I think our
observation is that they don't necessarily have the
tool, not the tools, the resources available to be able to
actually carry out enforcement in this way.
But it's sometimes more about, and I think they've said it themselves, it's
actually about the teeth, not so much the resources.
What would make it easier for community law to take some of those consumer
cases, particularly around
the coercion, harassment kind of conduct issues rather than
they, with, "I've got a consumer here who's paying more than they
intended to pay through use of
sort of discriminatory pricing techniques"?
How, what would make it easier for us to?
Yeah. Like if you were designing a system where community law was taking a bunch of
cases and they were sort of consumer cases and you're going to the courts or using
dispute tribunal-
Yeah
... whatever that was to do that, what would that look like?
Well, we're doing that now really in terms of making complaints and then raising
these kinds of issues at the disputes tribunal.
Mm-hmm.
Harassment and coercion, you can't do that.
But misleading, deceptive, that kind of thing we're raising in the disputes
tribunal, yeah, as those kind of arguments.
Yeah.
Yeah. As to your, the point about...
I think some of that drip pricing stuff,
that does affect a lot of consumers.
I wouldn't say necessarily that it just affects, the drip pricing just affects one
person, that it's the way that the process works
online for multiple consumers to buy in that way.
And that you sign up for this, but next thing you know you've actually signed up
for three years of a subscription to something or
add-ons to things that
you didn't really know you were signing up to.
So it affects more than the one. Yeah.
What would it take for community law to be running a class action around those
issues?
Hmm.
Yeah.
Hmm. Yeah, that's a really good question.
Resources, those cases are really intensive and we have
a lot of pro bono support through Te Ara Ture, and we're actually doing some
litigation work and intervening in cases now.
Te Ara Ture is our pro bono clearing house.
But they're so resource intensive.
You have to think about even when we're doing family law and sort of straying a
bit, but you can either represent people and
spend that time doing that, and that's really time and resource intensive, or
helping multiple people. So it really is a balancing of our resource.
Hmm. I mean,
that's open to us to do. It's a resource question. Yeah.
Thanks, Karen, for your submission today and appreciate the work you're doing as
well.
Thank you.
Thank you. Members, we actually have Tony Gavaghan.
Are you happy to present now a little bit ahead of schedule?
Sure.
We might hear from you, and then we'll have just a
short break.
If that's all right.
So we've got Tony and Marcus.
That's right.
On behalf of Fort Stafford Limited.
Thank you. We've got you for 10 minutes, gentlemen, but please leave some time for
questions at the end of that if you'd like.
Good morning. I'm Marcus Ganley from Franks Ogilvie.
We're on as special counsel. I'm here with Tony Gavaghan, and we're appearing on
behalf of Port Stafford and JFL.
Our submission is really focused on our client's practical experience in dealing
with a major fair trade issue centered on a breach of one of the fundamental
provisions of the act.
Section 9 of the FTA deals with misleading and deceptive
conduct.
Our submission is inspired by the experience of the Feltex litigants
represented by Mr. Gavaghan on behalf of Fort Stafford and JFL who lost
significant sums following
what the Supreme Court found to be a breach of Section 9 of the Fair
Trading Act.
Despite the Supreme Court finding statements in the Feltex share prospectus
breached Section 9 of the FTA, there has been no remedy for
investors.
Among the objectives of the bill in front of this committee are to strengthen
deterrence of unfair trading conduct and to support
appropriate consequences for breaches.
The written submission sets out some changes that Port Stafford and JFL would like
the committee to consider that would both deter the kind of unfair
trading conduct seen in the Feltex case,
and so that if a case like this were to emerge in 2027,
investors would have remedies and there would be appropriate consequences for the
breaches.
Appreciate the members read the submission, so we won't dwell on the prospective
recommendations.
This morning, what we'd like to do is focus on the lack of a remedy for the losses
suffered by Feltex investors following breach of the Fair Trading Act.
I'd like to pass to Mr. Gallie to speak to this experience and the solutions he's
hoping the committee will consider.
Good morning.
Thank you for hearing us.
The previous submitter touched on
the reality that Section 9 attempts to
achieve all of the objectives set out in the
very first explanatory note of the bill.
And inevitably, you will come into a financial
consequence,
and inevitably, you will come into small
amounts of harm done to a large number
of people, and you will very soon find
yourself in the place we found ourselves in
2008 of having to bring a class
action. And my partner, Patricia Mills, who died
last October, and
I forged or helped forge the class action regime in New Zealand.
And yet, having started out on this path in 2008,
and I have a copy here of the decision we obtained in
2018, and here we are eight years later, we
have a finding of an offense under Section 9.
The total amount of the compensation we seek is
215 million kiwi,
which is about a month's interest on the 27
billion US sitting in New York and Switzerland
from the forced merger of Credit
Suisse by its regulator for its bad
behavior.
So here we are in New Zealand. We've got Section 9.
We're a legacy case under Section 9 because it all happened
in 2004.
Sian Elias said that the Fair Trading Act
applied, and she said, "Look, I don't even know why you're bringing a class
action, because the regime of Section 9
is to help individuals on a me-too
basis." But that hasn't happened either.
So we're here to ask, and we're a little bit
peripheral. We've suggested a way that we could
end up with a remedy as part of this process.
We are open to your suggestions for how
3,639 New Zealand
families get their KiwiSaver back.
They lost 15, 16, $20,000 per
home. Today, if that was in a
proper fund, that would be 60 or $70,000, which is the
average KiwiSaver balance of the average 60-year-old.
If we are to push the superannuation age out
two years, for example, they'll need that $60,000 of
KiwiSaver to pay themselves at age 65 and
66. So it's an important amount of money that they lost.
It was two years before KiwiSaver came in, so they put their money
in what they thought was
a safe, well-branded enterprise.
So we're here to ask for your help to get the 215 million back.
We're open to how you suggest we do that.
We're available to work with you.
Thank you. Just to kick off,
so your submission today,
is it purely for the claimants you represented, and/or is
it to actually embed some shift into the proposed
legislation to prevent that from happening to others?
Well, both. And
we think this is a great bill. We support it.
You will inevitably need a class action regime.
What better place to take the Law Commission's
suggestion from 2022
and try it
as part of this bill?
Little people haven't got the amounts of money that you
need. The ASB wrote checks in May.
My partner's estate received
$517,000
from overcharged fees.
Davey Salmon QC oversaw a class action that achieved
135 million, and there's another 140-odd coming from
ANZ sometime.
So this is not a problem that's going away.
You've identified there's a problem out here to get
people made whole.
And to be clear, we're not suggesting in the submission that this committee try
to provide for a general class action regime.
It's a class action regime relating to the FTA, which would be in scope of this
bill.
Thank you. Dr. Davis.
Yeah, so just on your last comment,
why in front of the FTA rather than having a discussion with the
Financial Markets Conduct Authority?
Because
the predecessor to the FMA was the Securities Commission.
Right.
The whole reason for the class action was that the Securities Commission
said nothing to see here.
And we proved to the Supreme Court there was something to see,
and we had to do that ourselves.
So in light of that evidence,
why is it that you're not talking to the FMA now?
Because
we think that Section 9 of the Fair Trading Act
has got the general scope
that needs to be looked at. When you have to-
In terms of a collection of individuals?
Yes.
Okay.
Because-
Each individual then sits under their Fair Trading Act is what you're saying?
Or, and if they don't, they ought to.
Right.
Thank you. Arena
Tony, great submission. Thank you very much for
highlighting
a pretty significant
set of decisions in New Zealand's law
that we are still trying to work through today, and you're watching us do that in
real time. And you're right that
community law was answering on the same issues around how difficult it
is under the fair trading context to bring these very
small disputes to, and we have
either that mechanism or the Commerce Commission having
a big enforcement arm. But in New Zealand, we don't have that
either.
So we've got option A and option B, and we've chosen neither.
Tony, do you think that we will receive probably advice on your submission,
which tells us that it's outside of the scope of the bill?
What would you put to officials as
this is clearly a real-world problem, it's something which New Zealand hasn't
grappled with, but if we are told that it's outside the scope of the bill, how do
you think we should proceed as a committee where I'm sure there is-
Marcus speaks their language
Look, it's a very fair point, and we think the prospective
recommendations we put are within scope.
But on the relief scheme, that is a fair
question.
And I think the fundamental point
that Tony's reiterated to me a number of times,
there needs to be a solution.
We have a right here without a remedy.
We have a breach of the FDA found by the Supreme Court.
This is not Tony's argument. This is not the
investors saying that there was a breach.
This has been found by the Supreme Court to be a breach.
This may not be the right solution.
It's a way of tackling the problem. If not this, what?
It is now past time for action on this.
As Tony says, this is three and a half thousand people who've lost their savings
based on a breach of Section 9,
and it's time to find a remedy.
Thank you, gentlemen. Appreciate your submission today.
Thanks.
Yeah, thanks for coming in.
Thank you.
Members, we might just break for five, 10 minutes. Do you want 10 or five?
Well, give me five minutes. I was actually on the list before them, Kay Jones.
Great.
You were actually at 11:25, but-
We've actually got you for 11:25.
Yeah, she's here.
Does anybody want to-
But I was just meaning, you know, I'm here-
Yep
... that was-
Yep, go for it.
Yep, okay. Well-
Go for it. We're just-
Come on up
... sorry, we're just a bit of
flexibility this morning.
We'll see if Retail NZ can get here early.
Yeah, they are coming in early.
Great. Fantastic.
Wonderful.
Thanks, Kay. We're in your hands.
Sorry. Kia ora, committee.
It's good to see some familiar faces here from a few other areas,
and this is not as polished a submission as I sometimes
try and deliver. So I just want to cover, if I have time, three points,
but I'll start with the first one, which is
Section 43E, which gives an out to
advertisers. I raise in my submission the issue about
Facebook being effectively an advertising company,
and a lot of the complaints that I get from
an online community group of over 2,000 people includes the
fact that they do not take action on scams and fake
information. So what I'd suggest is there be a third
part to 43E, which says that if
advertisers receive information and they think it's okay and they have no reason to
believe it's not, then that's a defense.
But I think where if you have a third part, that where the
advertiser has been advised that there is fraudulent
activity,
then that removes the defense. Now, I'm not sure on how it
would be worded, but one of the issues is that
Meta, AKA Facebook, used to take action after five
complaints on an issue. Now they won't move until they've got
19 or more complaints on an issue, and even
then, when a
company page is put up as being, "Hey, we're having a closing down
sale," and the real company that's had this fake put up, it
complains, everybody else complains, and Facebook says, "Nothing to see here," and
allows it to go. So there's no responsibility, and I appreciate that big
tech companies are really difficult to deal with, but I think this regime
still needs to look at that. So even in principle, if you had a
third part to 43E,
saying that where the concerns had been raised,
then that would be a removal of defense.
It could be part of that whole discussion of how does Aotearoa New Zealand
deal with the powers that big tech companies are having and not
actually paying attention to complaints from people
here. I give a link in my submission to a story
about how difficult it is to do that.
My second point relates to the difficulty that
ordinary people in the community have about taking action.
Now, as I've said, it used to be I could phone up the Commerce Commission or
make contact and they would take action.
Well, the volume is such that that's not really feasible.
But at the same time,
people don't always know, is this just a problem I'm having, or
is this a problem that so many other people are having?
So if someone like the Commerce Commission could set up a dashboard or some kind
of register so that my complaint about New
World's Club Plus could be listed and other people
having it, it's not necessarily going as far as a class action,
but it's having a way of raising the significance
of an issue to make it easier to take action on it.
So I'm not sure exactly where that would fit in it, but when
we're moving from a-
... criminal
agency based to a civil liability.
We need to give people in the community more
ability to actually be part of the system.
Just like, if you have a pothole or overflowing drains in
Wellington, you can go to Wellington Council's Fix It form or
phone number or whatever. There's lots of ways of actually registering the
concern to get it handled. So what I'd like, I've suggested
a dashboard or some kind of digital system to register complaints so that
people can act on it.
And while I'm here, I will just touch briefly on the New World Club
Plus issue that I'm confronted with.
You may have seen the advertising on television and all the stuff about Shop
Smarter.
Mm.
I don't know if you're aware that Club Plus is now
denying online shopping rights to
anybody who does not use a mobile phone.
Now, I have mild disabilities, and I don't
use a mobile phone. This used to be a mobile phone,
and it's got accessibility features, but New Zealand Telcos have stopped
service to it, so I no longer have a phone I can use.
And I used to, during COVID lockdowns, do
online deliveries from New World or click and
collect. Now they're saying I can't get those.
I've registered for the card, but I cannot log in. I cannot do the shopping.
I've spoken with the Human Rights Commission legal team, and yes,
structural discrimination, and I'm looking at things.
But it's like,
I'm not probably the only person who is confronted with this issue
of denial of a service, which, yes, it is also part of the Fair
Trading Act,
because it disadvantages me. But it's not a financial disadvantage
directly. It's not enabling me
to get a service that I would otherwise be entitled to.
Anyway, so any questions, happy to take that, and I know that the
case I gave is perhaps outside the scope of looking at this.
But it is part of the online digital space that we're moving into, how
do people actually get rights when we're moving from
going into a shop physically and buying something to trying to order online?
Yeah. Thank you, Kay, for your submission.
We have actually met time, but appreciate you coming in and presenting to us-
Brilliant ... in person.
Yes, no, I'll be seeing a few members this afternoon for another submission,
so.
Thank you, Kay. Good. Thank you. Appreciate it.
Jayden, Tara,
how are we going?
We've
Oh, yeah? Yeah. Members, are you happy just to continue?
Yeah, let's-
Press on.
Push through.
Webb Henderson. Very good.
Kia ora koutou. Can everybody hear and see us?
Yes, good morning. We have you for 10 minutes.
Please take your submission as read, but love to have some time for questions.
Absolutely. Thank you, committee, for making the time to
speak with us today and hear the submissions.
We've been advising on the Fair Trading Act for about 30 years, and
I have with me Vicki Fallow, who has the benefit of having been at
the Crown Prosecutor's office. Meredith Connell acted for the commission
as well as obviously now in private practice in New Zealand.
So she's got a really good perspective on both the commission
side of enforcement as well as the private practice advisory piece.
So, we've got a couple of key points.
The first one is
in relation to process. So I'll cover that, and
then Vicki will cover off the matters relating
to move to a civil regime and other
technical changes. So, if you just bear with us, I'll deal
first with the process point.
And that is that we have submitted, both in relation to the
changes to the Commerce Act, the governance of the Commerce Commission,
and now here in relation to the Fair Trading Act, that it is really
important to
put into the
enforcement framework with the Commerce Commission a provision for a hearing
officer. Now, the concept here is really
about making sure that there is an administrative,
cost-effective way for natural justice rights
of participants and commission processes to be dealt with
that is short of needing to bring judicial review, which is costly,
time-consuming, takes up court time, and is also
quite confrontational for a number of organizations that really do
want to ensure that they maintain a strong relationship with the Commerce
Commission. And broadly speaking, when there are issues
relating to process,
they would want to raise them directly with the commission and have them dealt with
effectively and administratively.
So,
no organization is perfect. The commission is not perfect.
Nobody is expecting them to be perfect.
We have
dealt with the commission where they have process issues like
a failure to follow a proper process or to have put particular questions
to
individual parties under investigation, which has
resulted in potentially a preemptive decision,
which we would say is wrong. And frankly, we would've produced different evidence
if process had been
undertaken differently.
The commission will revisit its decision if you put
to it natural justice concerns-
But there is a lack of transparency in how that's
done. And so, of course, when the commission does revisit
its decision and come to the same decision, sometimes quite quickly, there is a
question on the part of the
participants as to whether that process was undertaken
as thoroughly as it might. So there's a perception of independence issue here,
as much as
the process being followed, in
fact, comprehensively and fulsomely.
And we see a real benefit in having that hearing officer process as
effectively a watch for administrative
natural justice concerns, and also having an ability to do
things like make interim orders or to review, I
think we're going to get to infringement notices in a bit, to have that
function that can ensure that from a legal
process perspective, those infringement
notice powers and powers of the commission generally are being
exercised fairly. Because the penalties that the Commerce
Commission can
negotiate or seek from the court are significant, both in the
criminal and the civil regime.
So that is our first submission. I'll hand over to Vicky to deal with the balance
of the submissions from Webb Henderson.
Thank you, Sarah.
Firstly, just wanted to raise the general point that Webb Henderson does
strongly support the move to a mainly civil regime.
In our experience, a lot of the conduct that falls under the Fair
Trading Act isn't a natural fit for criminal prosecution,
and is in fact a sort of outlier on the global stage
where this kind of conduct is generally something that attracts civil liability,
not criminal liability. And that becomes a real impediment
to global companies in particular, when faced with the option
to either admit criminal misconduct or fight a case.
It's a much bigger decision when there is criminal liability in play.
So we think this is long overdue and a good decision to move to a generally civil
regime.
At the same time, we do support the retention of criminal liability
for conduct which is truly criminal in nature.
So the pyramid schemes are a good example of that.
That is a type of conduct which is genuinely criminal, and has
significant public harm. And so we'd support continued criminal liability for those
kinds of offenses.
As Sarah mentioned, one thing that does naturally flow from that
move is the removal of infringement offenses.
However, we do think that there is some benefit in retaining an
ACCC style provision where you can
have an infringement notice issued on a no admission of liability basis, because
something we do see a lot when advising in practice is that
companies are unwilling to have an admission of liability on the
books, but may otherwise want to
discuss with the commission how to resolve without court proceedings.
So we think something like that which would allow the
commission to settle something without an admission of
liability will probably mean a lot less court time being
used. The balance of our written submissions
are effectively detailed drafting points.
But one thing that I did want to raise is that while they do all
seem quite technical, the importance of them is
that when we are advising on these types of matters, we need
to be able to tell our clients what will happen and what the
pathway will look like. And a lot of the drafting comments at the back end of our
submission go to clarity over what the process will be
when particular avenues are taken or when particular ancillary orders
are sought alongside substantive proceedings.
And as well as that, there are a couple of
examples of things where it seems that the intention
was not to, for example, remove Section 9 from the
bill, but I think that has been done potentially as an oversight.
So those are the balance of the submissions at the back end.
Those are the general submissions that we have for you today, unless you have any
questions for us.
Thank you. I do like your point. I had to pay a parking fine the other day, but
I didn't want to admit, I didn't want to assume that I was guilty,
but I thought I better pay the bill while
I- ... while I had the day so I can talk from firsthand experience.
Very important.
We've got a question from David Wilson, and then Avina.
Interested in your view around the role of a hearing officer.
But one line jumped out at me, and that was in
your subsection 11, that the hearing officer to intervene or
express a view that the commission would be bound to follow.
And I do like some of the subclauses there, like
issuing a stop now letter or such like, but the bound to follow
jumped out at me. Could you explain that a little further?
Yes, so we have borrowed the hearing officer concept from the
European Union, that has that within the European
Commission structure.
And
because it is a
technical
function within the commission,
we don't regard it as being problematic
for the commission to effectively be bound by another part
of the commission. It's still within the same administrative framework.
And so it would be sort of an internal commission
binding its own conduct as opposed to it being a court or
some other external party binding it.
And so for that, in terms of the
recommendations that are going through at the moment around
governance of the Comcom,
how would that relate
You would have a separate commissioner that would be a hearing officer, just like
we used to have cease and desist commissioners.
They would need to be legally qualified, and capable
effectively of performing a role similar to an ombudsman or
like all formal cease and desist commissioners.
And that function could sit within the commission as
a separate specialist commissioner within that structure.
Thank you for advice. It's the words bound to follow that still jump out at me.
My question is also related to Dr. David Wilson's.
The EU structure observes is a part of their current regime
for class actions referred from submitters
today, around
the importance of having a
way for some of the consumer protections designed
in this bill to be brought by a number of small,
low-value cases.
What's your observation about whether
what you've proposed should be also used in the way that, say,
the submitter directly prior to you was proposing?
Yeah, and those were really well-made points
from the submitter prior to us which we agreed with.
The class action framework is very difficult.
And so, you could certainly see a hearing officer
having jurisdiction to consider the
administrative, effectively speeding fines as
the member described before,
where those speeding fines could then
benefit those smaller consumers because our firm
does a lot of class action, particularly in Australia.
We supervise a lot of class action litigation.
And all I would say is that you need quite a big class, and you
need them to have quite large
damages
in order for it to get off the ground,
because running any court case is an expensive process.
And so if the commission could have a separate structure, which is
effectively like an administrative penalty imposer
that would be, I think, very helpful, particularly in the New
Zealand context, where the level of damages frankly just doesn't ever
justify the class actions.
Agree.
You
also made a submission on the
criminal versus civil penalties.
Mm-hmm.
That's something we don't support, but I'd be interested in your
views on whether you think it's appropriate to be able to insure for the full range
of the civil penalties. Obviously, one of the benefits of
having more criminality within the regime is
that people are personally liable for their decisions, and
insurance has an impact on the way that they would make
those
decisions. And also whether you think that directors should be able to
use the corporate veil in some of these
sorts of conduct that are more like unconscionable
conduct.
To take a view from you on that.
Yeah, that's a really good question.
Couple of points. First, I don't know if you're aware about this, but our
experience in market is that most insurance policies entirely exclude
Fair Trading Act and Commerce Act from statutory liability policy anyway.
So a lot of conduct under this act is actually not
insured, not because it's criminal, but just because it's not insured,
because it's out of the scope of statutory liability.
The second point is that commission, both under civil and criminal
regime, can
name individual directors. And from my perspective, it's actually
less about whether it's a potential criminal liability
or not because ultimately no one's going to jail on this
stuff anyway. It's only Commerce Act that that happens.
It's actually more to do with being named.
So directors don't want their reputation tarnished by being
personally named, and it doesn't matter whether it's a civil or criminal
proceeding. And the commission can always name individual directors under
both regimes.
Did you have-
Thank you. I think we'll have to close it out there. We have met time.
Gone a little bit over, actually. But thank you very much for your submission.
Thanks.
We appreciate it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for the questions.
We're now going to the Law Association of New Zealand.
I believe they're online.
Hi, can everyone hear me?
Yes.
Welcome.
Yeah, I'm just expecting one more colleague as well, Ben. Yep, he's here.
Yeah.
Okay, great. Happy for us to kick it off, then?
Yes, go for it.
Thank you.
First of all, we represent the Law Association's Technology and Law Committee.
I believe we had colleagues from the civil litigation committee who also put in a
submission, but they're not here today.
And we might be a bit out of our depth if we were posed questions
regarding that. But otherwise,
yeah, I just want to introduce that we are a committee of lawyers and
legal practitioners or legal professionals who work in the areas of law and
technology. We have expertise in these areas, but not all of us are lawyers.
I'm not a lawyer. I actually work in content moderation and trust and safety
for an AI video platform, Synthesia.
So a lot of hands-on stuff with scam disruption.
And I believe Ben here is a litigation lawyer, so he might be able to speak better
to the litigation questions.
But anyway, representing our committee, we are primarily focused on the Section 48U
defense, the safe harbor provision for digital service providers.
And
generally, very briefly put, we do think this provision needs a lot more work
before it could be fit for purpose.
And we have some concerns that the work that would be required to get there
is quite
large in scope and would involve asking some very difficult questions that many
other jurisdictions around the world are still currently grappling with and have
not reached an easy solution at. So I understand we've dumped on you quite
a meaty submission for just one provision.
So I had a preamble prepared, but I'm happy to just take questions if it'd
be better if we just jump to those.
There doesn't appear to be any questions yet, so maybe if you just want to touch
on-
Okay. I'll just summarize our position and-
Yeah
... we'll see where that goes then. Sure.
So the current wording of Section 48U, we observe
some glaring gaps, which we believe threatens to undermine its main objective
of encouraging proactive scam disruption activity.
One big concern we have is with the requirements to reverse the decision.
That does not require service providers to consider contradictory evidence or
provide accessible mechanisms for affected users to appeal any actions taken.
And so it would
effectively leave platforms without accessible appeal and review channels in a
safer position under this defense, and hence actually incentivize them
to avoid investing in systems and customer support to the
detriment of the consumer. That's outlined mainly in subsection three
of our submission.
We're also concerned with how the
section fails to address the use of artificial intelligence and autonomous
review tools, which are already widely used in this industry.
And if this act doesn't address those points more clearly,
we can pretty much guarantee you if this defense were brought to a
trial, this would be litigated very extensively.
It won't be an easy question, so it would not really go very far
deterring action in the way that we believe this defense was originally intended to
achieve.
And, also just from a policy perspective, we're not convinced that there's a
sufficient justification for this defense in the first place.
There are already massive, very significant barriers and practical considerations
which discourage the civil actions this defense is seeking to deter.
We're not persuaded that this defense would be particularly effective at deterring
the actions entirely even then, as it still retains a lot of ambiguity
on the main points which these actions which would be conducted
under contract law and existing contractual frameworks.
We're not really persuaded that
the defense would do anything to address these as the main points, such as the
reasonableness standards of action taken would still need to be fleshed
out in a case.
So overall, our committee is agreeable that there is benefit to be had from
providing a clearer framework on where potential
liabilities in these issues could lie.
It's important that we give these service providers more certainty and also
enhance confidence to take proactive action against online scam activities.
However, these need to be balanced with appropriate safeguards to ensure that
anti-consumer practices are not actively incentivized, which we see the current
state of the bill doing to an extent,
to the detriment of legitimate good faith users.
Hence,
we see possible steps forward in perhaps two tiers.
Our current position is that this Section 48U defense, as it's worded, might
actually make the status quo worse.
In order for it to at least not make things worse,
we think there
needs
to be a requirement for the defense to apply that platforms
provide a meaningful appeal mechanism in order to not have that
loophole that incentivizes
bad customer service and
product design. And also, we think that the scope
might want to be narrowed a bit because currently the defense captures a
very broad range of platforms with differing business models
and profit incentives. We believe that the current section is tailored very well
to suit the needs of, say, the internet service providers, telecommunication
providers, and those that work in a domain
name service site. But it seems at odds with the business
models of platforms like Facebook, YouTube, Google, who provide
free services and get their revenue through other ways, because this would nudge
them towards more anti-consumer practices, which we believe is not something
we want to see. It's already hard enough for people who rely on their
services. But to also take it further, we believe that for this
defense to really bring about a benefit to the current legal
regime, we would like to see more certainty in the provisions
about where the use of AI and autonomous review tools would sit
within any proposed reasonableness standard.
But we understand it's a very difficult question.
That's a fundamentally existential one, if anything.
Many jurisdictions around the world are struggling with this right now, and I
think our committee convener would describe
it as, "This is an entire PhD topic.
It's not something we can resolve within a year or a month."
Yeah. That basically sums up our position.
Happy to take any questions if any have come up now.
Thank you.
Arina, did you have one?
Yep. Just a quick question. Might be more for Ben.
Yes, the provision is designed
to get to ISPs and telco providers
because they are providing a necessity of life,
and
people do rely on them. I disagree with you.
It's pretty blunt in their favor. If anything, you could argue that it was
anti-consumer, but I don't think you could argue that it was
at once pro-ISP and vague.
They will definitely be able to rely on it.
So is your argument that it needs to be more
pro-consumer?
I just think
personally,
the issues with
how it's framed aren't sort of pro-consumer or
pro-telco. I think from a
litigation perspective, it's the complexities of raising and arguing the
defense firstly. Which on their face,
I do think the
provisions are currently more pro
the telcos and ISPs,
in the sense that,
as Isaac pointed out, you don't have these review
mechanisms mandated.
So there is this
potential opportunity for them to be abused,
the safe harbor provision to be abused.
But-
Yes
... I think it's anti
anti the telcos and ISPs in the sense that
in the situations where they should be
legitimately relying on it,
it's not a slam dunk safe harbor.
There is a lot of litigation that would need to be teased out
in order to invoke the
safe harbor.
And that comes down to just, I guess, the amount of layers that there are to it,
but also there's reasonable-
So just to press that, so you think that you could take a case for
someone who was sending thousands of text messages out in a day for a
legitimate purpose, who had been banned by their telco
from sending that. You think that's possible
under the current formation?
In what sense do you mean? I guess the-
I think it's a really blunt safe harbor, and that's what's intended.
So I'm asking you, do you think-
To the extent that they can rely on it, I think if
a telco was to rely on it, say to seek summary judgment or
strike out early on-
Yeah
... there are a lot of steps that need to be jumped through.
And a lot of ways, I think, for potential litigants to press the
telcos and ISPs to prove their reliance on that safe
harbor. A lot of it goes to knowledge of the telco and the ISP and the
reasonable steps they took in reliance of those things, which
in and of itself is going to be very factually intensive and probably
require some pretty substantive hearings in court, I would imagine.
Okay, we'll put that to advisors. That's great.
And if I may respond to that further as well, because I noticed you mentioned the
point-
Oh, well, sorry. Isaac, we're just going to call it there for time.
Okay.
But yeah, thank you both for your submission today. Really appreciate it.
There's a lot of detail in there.
Yes, AI statements.
We now-
Thank you
We're going to move to Retail New Zealand here.
Yeah, thank you for joining us a little bit ahead of schedule this morning.
We appreciate
that.
You're familiar with the process, obviously.
We've got 10 minutes with you, so yeah, feel free to save some time if we...
Sure. Morning, everyone. Thank you very much for the time.
Just to introduce, my name's Carolyn Young, I'm the chief executive.
I'm Denise Garland. I'm the advocacy manager at Retail NZ.
So look, I think you'll have read our submission.
I'll just highlight a couple of points.
Denise will probably say a couple of things, and then we'll open up for questions.
Retailers in general, well, generally speaking, all of our retailers, they support
the Fair Trading Act and the intent of what the purpose of the Fair Trading Act
is there for, and businesses want to comply to the Fair
Trading Act.
There's a couple of things we just want to highlight in terms of
the
way this is framed at the moment could end up not
meeting the end need of what you're looking to do.
So
one of the first things really is about being proportionate to what
has actually occurred and making sure that for a small retailer or
a small business, that if there's a mistake that's been occurred and
they're fined, that it wouldn't put them out of business and close their business,
because I don't think that anybody is wanting that to happen on a regular basis.
So there needs to be something in the bill that
enables an interpretation to be made around whether there was an
intention to the error that has occurred,
or was it just merely a mistake, like a genuine error?
So really understanding the difference between
a billing error is different than false advertising.
Or if someone's put stock on the wrong shelf, you've had a
staff member, they've inadvertently put stock on the wrong shelf instead of
where it should be.
Or
we've just come from the Governance Administration Committee, where we were
discussing
the overseas bank transfers, and one of the things there was about the
disclosure of fees and fees being
really visible to consumers and businesses.
So there's different ways banks and
those providers are promoting those at the
moment that you could say is less than
truthful, and so you really want things to be really
open and clear. But if there is an error, if someone's made a
mistake, that that's taken into account with the size of the penalty
that's applied. So it needs to be proportionate for what's actually occurred, and
I don't know that it, or we don't feel that it covers that right at the
moment. And then there's a piece around
streamlining product safety settings so that
we support the move to having a global product safety setting because there's so
many of our products come in from overseas that it would make some sense.
We just have to think about what that transition looks like to make sure that
there's plenty of time for businesses to adjust, sell their existing
stock that may or may not partly or fully comply now, so that there's
an easy transition for everyone to understand.
So I think that would be the key thing there, and then I think Denise was going to
talk a little bit about
the enabling the scam safe harbor piece.
Yeah. We're very much in support of that.
We just feel like there needs to be a little bit more clarity
in terms of telecommunications providers, online payment
service providers. They often use third parties around
helping them determine fraudulent or scam
disruptors, and without
essentially explicitly enabling those third
parties or a IP address
or particular payment being considered on this
watch list, we're concerned that that'll put too much
onus on telecommunications and online service providers to
be making those calls themselves, and so therefore not having the
ability to act quickly when there is reasonable grounds to
consider that there may be scam or fraudulent activity
occurring.
Thank you. We've got a question from Dr. Deborah Russell.
Thank you.
I just
want to go to the product safety standards.
You said you needed some kind of transitional
period in there. Are you envisaging something like
as long as it complies with the New Zealand standard that is now being superseded
by an international standard or whatever it is?
But it-
Yes, obviously complying with New Zealand standards now would be appropriate.
And then, and making sure that if the overseas standard is higher, that there's a
period of time for us to get to that point so that existing stock can be sold.
Because a lot of stock and manufacturing is done six or nine
months or 12 months in advance.
Yeah.
So there needs to be time for businesses to make sure they are either changing
or changing where their supply comes from.
Good point. Yeah. So-
So we agree with the-
Certainly once the new standard is in place, if they then buy stuff that is
not consistent with the new standard, we wouldn't want that.
No.
No. But if they've, in good faith, placed orders that...
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah.
That seems reasonable. I just want to go back to the
discussion you had about
genuine mistake versus intent.
Mm.
And I get the point, except that sometimes mistake upon
mistake upon mistake starts to look like intent.
So that should be considered as well, right?
Yeah.
So I think if we think about it, if it's recidivist
offending-
Yeah
... then I think that
should be taken into consideration, because obviously there's no learnings that
have been put in place in terms of that business.
And we do want to make sure that consumers are getting
what they should be getting and that it's really clear.
So it's just that differential between making sure if someone does make a
mistake, that that's taken into account in terms of the penalty that they have.
And if they are a small business, that the size of the penalty, I haven't got it
off the top of my head, but the size of the penalty's quite big, like it's a
million dollars or something like that-
Yeah
... or 10% or whatever.
That's quite a lot for a SME.
Mm-hmm.
And so that would just close them down.
And if it was an error,
then it should be a bit more proportionate.
But if it was egregious,
then that should also be taken into account.
Yeah.
Thank you, Dr. Deborah Russell. I'm interested in your point about
the scam safe harbor in that there's a high onus on
the platforms
and the telcos. So just a simple question.
If not them, then who?
Well, we are recommending that essentially
these third-party providers that help support
telecommunications and payments providers be
included in the safe harbor or there be
a provision that if these,
I guess, IP addresses or whatever it is that is making these transactions that are
considered to be potentially or quite likely to
be fraudulent or scams, that that is grounds enough
to be
reasonable grounds to suspect that it's
scam activity. It is around, I guess, there's not enough clarity
as to what would determine the reasonable grounds
and whether it's up to each individual telecommunications
provider or online service provider, which currently
don't have the abilities to do this work
themselves, which is why they
engage with third-party providers, which are much more
equipped to, and they obviously do their due diligence
before employing them to help them with this work.
But just ensuring that that is captured within the safe harbor.
There's just a bit of concern that otherwise the onus goes back onto these
providers themselves,
and that will then require them to take more time to be able to
shut down this activity because they themselves
don't have the same resources to necessarily
understand the goings on and find those reasonable
grounds.
So you're suggesting Internet New Zealand?
Potentially.
I'm not necessarily aware of exactly where that might stand,
but absolutely that could be a consideration for the committee. Yeah.
We could ask our, if you want us to ask our members where they think that would
sit, we can ask that specific question.
It's such a big issue, isn't it?
Mm.
You know? Who's going to actually detect.
Yeah. And the thing in the telco space, there are a lot
of fraudulent activities that happen at all sorts of different ways, whether
it's in person or online, that happen.
The same thing will happen across all the range of telcos.
If it happens at one, it will happen at Spark.
If it happens at Spark, it'll happen at Two Degrees and Skinny and so on
and so forth.
And it's really,
no matter what type of fraudulent activity, it's really bad.
I think that's a good place to end it.
Thank you both so much for your submission today.
Have you got any more submissions in Parliament today?
We are done today.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
You'll be back.
Lunchtime. See you tomorrow.
Yeah. Thank you for your work.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thank you. Chair.
Members, we're just going to take a few moments back in private with
officials just to wrap up or any comments, queries from our submitters to that.
So